the Buddha it praises seclusion in the
suitors in many places hmm so assuming
that that is what we should be doing
being so close secluded how can we get
ready for that situation what can we do
so that we can actually live in some
physical seclusion and actually benefit
from it right yeah the most obvious
thing is basically to start exposing
yourself to it the seclusion in other
words you're not gonna prepare yourself
for seclusion if you never leave the
group if you if you never even leave the
group for the periods of time if you
never spend time alone if you're always
surrounded by people the preparedness
for seclusion cannot come out of it
because it's completely the opposite of
it so as helpful as people can be for
one's well-being and so on it's a
compromise needing others it's a
compromise whether it you know as a lay
person or a mark doesn't matter but when
I say need anything either I'm talking
more specifically about needing others
for your existential well-being that's a
massive risk that's that's a massive
compromise if you never sort of develop
out of it because you know that all
those reflections and we are all owners
of our actions nobody basically what you
do stays with you even if you live this
life then you go to the next one and
next one or whatever the point is no
other people can help you with that no
other people can take away your burden
all right it's just it's always on you
your intentions your decisions your
actions will always stay in you that's
women you've bound with your actions and
results of it so existentially
fundamentally you're alone whether you
want to be or not so the practice comes
out of the
the first step of recognition of their
very essential principle that you are
alone that you cannot be it's always the
experience is always me and others even
if others are your best closest friends
and partners and relatives and family
it's still others you can have very
close others but for you it's still just
you so when it comes to feelings your
intentions your responsibility that
cannot be shared among the group only as
an excuse basically said use it I feel I
can tell you that I feel like this yes
yeah but that dimension of your feeling
is inherently inaccessible to me in as
much as I mentioned my feeling is
inherently accessible to anybody other
than me so so it's it's not it doesn't
mean solitude is not optional in other
talks because existence is not optional
an existence is solitary basically and
that's why if somebody wants to overcome
and undo bhava the existence you need to
start recognizing these inherent
principles of it so for as long as you
don't leave the group you how can you
how can develop a tautology
how can you see through it how can you
discern that that the neutral feeling
that the Buddha praises basically for
which solitude is required because
otherwise you're gonna have most people
who are not used to solitude when they
are left alone the boredom is the first
result of their experience so the
experience boredom which is kind of hard
just bored but it's actually much more
than just that because if you stay with
your boredom he starts turning into this
Restless panic fear and anxiety and and
that's when you realize how much you
actually depend on your perception of
others around you how much you depend on
that in order to basically conceal that
inherent nature existence that you are
alone and fundamentally you're not in
control either that's what people people
are so terrified of boredom generally
he's just it's it the whole existence
the whole lifestyle goes a
against that principle of existence that
you're not in your control that you are
alone so that's why every little
reminders of that are very frightening
for people who are no use to it
so of course you can't expect to just
jump into it overnight because yeah you
could legitimately lose your mind but at
the same time to use that as an excuse
to never do it and never prepare
yourself for it
well that's equally ignorant so you want
to recognize okay I'm I'm not ready to
jump into that extreme solitude right
away which means I should make myself
ready because what you think death is
and is there any different the basically
cessation cancellation of all of you
means of escape from yourself
cancelation of sensuality cancellation
of company cancellation of other
cancellation of distraction that's what
death is like its ultimate terror for a
petitioner who is fundamentally is
essentially dependent upon others upon
sensuality upon distraction so using
examples of people jumping into solid
too quickly losing the mind as a
proof that you should you shouldn't do
that well there's just non wisdom
speaking using examples to prove that
you can do it to quickly show which
means slow down a bit but that still
remains the goal whether you go to it
faster slowly does not compromise the
quality of the goal which is developing
of the solid ship so at that I mean
whether it's a layperson or a monk
doesn't matter you review your mind
reflect upon and see am I would I be
ready to live in solitude without having
anything to do without having any
interactions or at least for the
majority of my day would I be able to
just be with myself or would I have to
sort of extra commit to some sort of
meditation technique to keep doing this
basically just finding things to do
would I need things to do in the
solitude or will
would it be a tease so whatever the
answer did like exactly delighting in
solitude I'm I'm at ease in solitude I
prefer it but that takes work and
development and yeah I mean don't take
my word for it read the sutras and just
all the time till like learning how to
delight in solitude not because you
can't cope with others or because you
hate others all those are wrong reasons
and they're obvious they're going to
become obvious to whoever goes into
solitude no these are genuinely
preferring it over company preferring it
over interaction not because you're lazy
what I'm developed it's because you see
it as a basis of wholesome because you
see it as a as mirroring the principle
the basic existential principle that
you're not running away from and that's
through that discernment then it will
support mindfulness and everything else
that's the thing you ask yourself am I
ready for this no okay so as a layperson
I should really start preparing myself
for it even if I never go into complete
solitude ordain become a monk or
whatever I will get sick I will die my
senses will fail how do you think it
feels your sense is failing it feels
like you're basically being confined
more and more and more into one solitary
box imprisoned imprisoned that's what
the Buddha gave that simile of the four
mountains coming closer and closer from
every direction and crushing you
eventually as in you have less and less
space to move less and less possibility
of engaging with senses which means less
and less possibility of maintaining the
domain of sensuality the domain of
distraction so if your whole life is
about avoiding that but at the same time
you think you're practicing Dhamma
that's a complete contradiction in terms
nobody denies that others can helpful in
a group of like-minded people is helpful
but that's just in as much school is
helpful for somebody who is learning a
craft but they can't do the craft for
you so they can help you initially if
you perceive them as as knowing more
than you and so on that's why I like
finer if you find a friend it's equal or
superior yeah
learn from them not like associate for
somebody who knew you can't learn
anything from on the previous Adama but
still just because of the association in
itself and that before you or other sort
of code that suit about the noble
friendship it's quite obvious where the
Buddha meant by it very often you hear
that quote and it the holy friendship is
the and the whole of the holy life
having a good friend is like the entire
holy life and if the Buddha stopped
there then yeah you could say okay we
need friends but then the bullet goes in
the same suit that the next line and he
says what he meant by it he mended here
a young man hears about the Buddha and
the possibility of enlightenment because
of that he regards him as a friend at
that time and because of that friendship
in his mind towards such in such person
who maybe became enlightened he develops
faith on account of which he goes for it
becomes much and then becomes
enlightened and as a result of his
efforts that's exactly yeah that's the whole
that's exactly yeah that's the whole
meaning of that so yeah you find a the
good friend to learn from but not the
good friend to indulge your friendship
because you're too afraid to be alone or
too distracted or too anxious so it's it
really it's not negotiable at all that's
why whoever detained the right view in
the sutras all the Buddha would tell is
a go to solitude empty heart the root of
a tree do it do because you would need
that solitude for that and the person
with the right view would would actually
do it rightly they wouldn't be using
solitude for any wrong reasons so that's
what he would have a source just
constantly just repeating that and we
said that before when Ananda was with
all those other are Hansen audience
ohing robes for Katina and if we are
compared into a cup a band of fishermen
at the market shouting and I'm sure they
were very mindful and composed certainly
for our modern standards
yeah the Buddha wasn't mocking it this
is ridiculous what are you doing there
oh well Lord we are selling drugs for
Katinas on here like a band of fishermen
and then stop talking about the solitude
and seclusion and on socializing so I
mean you don't expect it overnight like
I'll do it
but that doesn't mean that you don't
start preparing yourself for it you want
to develop mental strength or any form
of strength you recognize your weakness
then you reckon is what you want to
develop but avoiding solitude would be
equivalent of you recognize your
weakness and then justify to yourself
that you shouldn't develop strength in
the first place
oh I can't go into soldier yeah you
shouldn't companies that go company see
the Buddhist said it's the noble
friendship but he didn't he said if the
noble friendship you find the friends
that at least theoretically were
developed more than you because of that
you try to match them because of that
friendship because of their trust you
try to match that development you try to
match that enlightenment of the Buddha
so yeah in that sense it was the
attitude of friendship they determine
your whole life as a monk as somebody
who practiced but not the actual social
socially interacting and engaging with
everyone and our one breath